Right, if
you want to talk, alright, afterwards.
Okay, so today we are is ערכין, Arachin, ערכין Arachin I should
say, ה, Heh, five. We pick up a little bit at the
bottom of ד עמוד ב. Dalet Amud Bet. So,
and we are discussing in the middle of the דרשה drasha of
טומטום tumtum and אנדרוגינוס, androgynous, that they can
be מעריך maarikh but not נערך. neerakh. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara is
saying, why would I have thought to exclude them from a נדר,
neder, from a vow? Because I mean the same way a person
can vow the value of a tree, you know, whose obviously their
gender doesn't matter. So גמרא Gemara says, no, here's the חידוש. chiddush.
The חידוש chiddush is, is that we learn from the פרשה parsha
of ערכין Arachin that even if you don't say the whole person,
even if you say their heart, their lungs, some vital organ, which
is referred to as כבודו, kevodo, that
that implies the whole person. And therefore, and that we learn to
apply that not only to ערכין Arachin but even in case of
נדר. neder. If you vow somebody's heart to pay their value, it's
basically their whole value. So there I might have said that that
idea that the vital organ represents the whole person is limited to
the people that are in the category of ערכין, Arachin, and I
would have excluded טומטום tumtum and אנדרוגינוס. androgynous. So this is telling
me that I don't do that. That that idea that the vital
organ represents the whole person is for everybody when you're doing the
market value, not even, not only people that are in the category
of ערכין. Arachin. But now the גמרא Gemara actually comes to directly
address that question and says, is that really true? Because yesterday we
ended with quoting an extensive ברייתא braita that says that if somebody
says the head of this slave, the head of this donkey I'm
donating to the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, that it does not represent
the whole thing, that actually it's like half of it, you and
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash are partners. So what is the story
when you say a vital organ and you donate it to that
value to the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, does it mean the entirety
or does it mean only like half of that animal? So let's
take a look as the גמרא Gemara now tries to answer that
question.
Can this be money? If he says...
Yes, you're not actually, yes, it depends. If you're actually saying sanctifying
the thing itself, then the thing itself is owned by the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash and if you wanted, and then you could redeem
it with money. If you said the value of the thing, then
it would, then you would give the money, it would not be
the thing itself. Okay, but so that's the question. We have a
whole ברייתא braita that says when you sanctify the head, you're giving
essentially half of it to the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So what
is it? Is it the whole or is it, or is it,
you know, part? So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara
says the four lines from the, five lines from the bottom, end
of the line, וחמור ופרה ליתנהו בערכין, v'chamor u'parah leitneihu b'Arachin, חמור,
chamor, a donkey, and ופרה, u'parah, a cow, ליתנהו בערכין, leitneihu b'Arachin,
are not in the category of ערכין, Arachin, ואינן נידון בכבודו, v'einan
nidon b'kevodo, and you see that they don't have this law of
כבודו, kevodo, which again means that their vital organ represents their entirety.
So why do you say that that would be true in a
טומטום tumtum and אנדרוגינוס? androgynous? So the גמרא Gemara says one minute.
There's a problem here bigger than whether you are in ערכין Arachin
or not. וטעמך, u'taamakh, the גמרא Gemara says according to your reasoning,
תיקשי לך עבד, tikshei lakh eved, how about the slave example? דאיתיה
בערכין, d'iteih b'Arachin, that actually is in the category of ערכין. Arachin.
And from ערכין Arachin we know that a vital organ represents the
entire self. So even by a slave where that's clearly the case,
in this ברייתא, braita, ואינו נידון בכבודו, v'eino nidon b'kevodo, this ברייתא
braita is saying that if you say the head of a slave,
it's not representing the entire self. So the גמרא Gemara says this
ברייתא braita is a problem. It's not whether you are in the
category of ערכין Arachin or not. This ברייתא braita indicates if you
sanctify the head of something, a person, an animal, whatever, it's like
half owned by the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. And we had been
saying that when you do the head or a vital organ, it's
the whole. What is the answer? Is it part or is it
whole when it's a vital organ? So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא
לא קשיא, ela lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא בקדשי מזבח הא
בקדשי בדק הבית. ha b'kodshei mizbeiach ha b'kodshei bedek habayit. There's a
difference between sanctifying it to the altar and sanctifying it to the
temple treasury. Now the logic I think at least intuitively would have
been the opposite of the גמרא Gemara because here by ערכין Arachin
we are basically talking about to the temple treasury. And similarly when
you're sanctifying a cow, a donkey, a slave, you're not doing it
as a קרבן, korban, you're doing it to the temple treasury. So
there it's about ownership. Now normally as opposed to a קרבן korban
which is about like its entire identity is as a קרבן korban
and something that is brought. So intuitively I would have said, and
we're going to have a case like this in a minute, that
if I say the head of this is an עולה, olah, so
that's definitional. עולה olah is either everything or nothing. It's about the
whole identity of the thing. So if I say a vital organ,
that logically should represent the entirety. If however it's about ownership and
property, I could say, okay, the head is owned by the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, the rest is owned by me. You know, there
you have more of a logical idea of splitting. The גמרא Gemara
somewhat ironically, because but it's necessary to resolve this contradiction, says the
reverse. If you were to sanctify it as a קרבן korban then
that is the case of the ברייתא braita where where the head
is only representing a. like a is only representing
a part. Whereas if you come to do it as a donation
to the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, there we say that if you
say a vital organ, it's like it's the whole thing. I can't
explain that like I said, the only explanation I could give would
be for the reverse, but that's what the גמרא Gemara says to
resolve it. We've been saying the head represents a whole part, that's
when it's to the temple treasury. When do we say you're partners
with the בית המקדש? Beit Hamikdash? That's when it's a קרבן. Korban.
Obviously you can't bring a half of an animal as a קרבן.
Korban. What it means is you redeem the money and use that
money to buy, to pay toward another קרבן. Korban. So let's take
a look. The גמרא's Gemara not done. Okay, so let's see where
the גמרא Gemara goes with this. במאי אוקימתא בקדשי מזבח. Bemai okimta
bekadshei mizbe'ach.
So you said when it- where is this that the head or
vital organ is only half? That's when it's for the- for the
altar. אימא סיפא, Eima seifa,
let's look at the end. ולא עוד, Velo od, not only that,
אלא אפילו אמר ראש פרה זו הקדש אין הקדש אלא ראשה. ela
afilu amar rosh para zu hekdesh ein hekdesh ela rosha. So up
until now we've been saying if you say the head it really
means half, but we said in the case of a cow if
you say the head it literally means the head. Why does it
literally mean the head? Because as we said people sell the head
of a cow in a butcher store. So therefore head there is
not meant metaphorically, it's meant literally as the head. That's what the
ברייתא. Braita. So other things you say the head you're half partners
with the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. Cow, the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash
really owns the head. So the גמרא Gemara says how could that
be? אמאי? Amai? How could that be that if you say the
head and it literally means the head? How could it be that
it's limited to that? If it really is about a קרבן? Korban?
תפשוט קדושה בכולה. Tifshot kedusha bekulah. Really,
once you're talking about a vital organ and about a קרבן, Korban,
and this is sort of the logic I said to you a
minute ago, there it should really spread throughout the entire thing. When
you're sanctifying for a קרבן Korban a vital organ, the logic is
the exact opposite of what we just said, that the entire thing
is a קרבן Korban because it's all about its identity. ומי לא
תניא, Umi lo tanya, did we not teach in a ברייתא? Braita?
האומר, Ha'omer, somebody says דף פ"ט עמוד א', daf pey-tet amud aleph,
רגלה של זו
עולה. raglah shel zu olah. So this- the leg of this cow
or whatever sheep is an עולה. olah. יכול תהא כולה עולה, Yachol
tehei kulah olah, maybe that defines the entire cow as an עולה?
olah? It's a leg. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, כל אשר יתן ממנו
לה' יהיה קדש. kol asher yiten mimenu l'Hashem yiheyeh kodesh. Anything that
you will give to God from it, ממנו, mimenu, from it will
be holy. ממנו קדוש, Mimenu kadosh, it's possible that only a part
of something is holy ולא כולה קדוש. velo kulah kadosh. So actually
if you sanctify the leg as an עולה, olah, it's not entirely
an עולה. olah. But that's a non-vital organ. We'll get to a
vital organ in a minute.
Isn't an עולה olah the whole animal?
Right, so that's the question. How by an עולה olah it's either
all or nothing, which is exactly the idea that the גמרא's Gemara
getting to, that when you talk about קרבנות, korbanot, how can you
speak about partial? But here it's saying that if it's a non-vital
organ it's possible. Now what do you do with it? So that's
going to be the next line of the גמרא. Gemara. What does
it mean to have a leg that's an עולה? olah? So the
גמרא Gemara says יכול תצא לחולין, yachol tetzei l'chullin, okay if it's
not all an עולה olah maybe I can just ignore it? תלמוד
לומר, Talmud lomar, יהיה, yiheyeh, it shall be, בהווייתה תהא, behavayatah tehei,
it retains its status. So how do you deal with an animal
that has a leg that's part that's an עולה, olah, has עולה
olah sanctity? So הא כיצד, ha keitzad, how do you deal with
it? תימכר לצורכי עולות, Timacher l'tzorchei olot, sell it to somebody who
wants to bring a קרבן עולה. korban olah. Charlie here I know
he needs to bring an עולה, olah, so I sell him my
sheep which already has the leg sanctified as an עולה. olah. So
when he brings it, he's then going to sanctify the whole thing
as an עולה. olah. He will bring it, the whole thing will
be brought as an עולה olah including the leg. Of course it's
not- for- I can't charge Charlie for the leg because the leg
doesn't belong to me anymore, it's already an עולה. olah. So I
sell it all to him, he's going to bring the whole thing
as an עולה, olah, he needs to bring an עולה olah anyway,
and I sell it to him
ודמיה חולין, udmeiha chullin, the money he pays for me- if he
pays for it I can use for whatever purpose because I really
sold him everything except the leg, so that's non-sanctified
money. חוץ מדמי אותו אבר שבה. Chutz midmei oto eivar shebah. However
the cost of the leg he doesn't have to pay for, that
wasn't mine to sell. So Charlie buys it minus the cost of
the leg, he gets a deal, and the whole thing gets brought
as an עולה, olah, so the sanctity gets used properly. Okay, that's
how you solve it. But the basic point is the leg has
קדושת עולה, kedushat olah, it does not define the whole קרבן. korban.
Doesn't it have to be a full-sized קרבן? korban?
Yeah, so the גמרא Gemara thank you very much I was trying
to word that but okay, the גמרא Gemara asks הכא במאי עסקינן
hacha bemai askinan if Charlie is obligated in a קרבן, korban, he-
he obligated himself in an עולה, olah, well he only brought a-
he only brought
a 9/10ths of an עולה, olah, he didn't- the whole thing wasn't
an עולה olah because of him. So the גמרא Gemara speaks about
how he undertook his obligation in a way that gave him a
little latitude. Okay, he didn't say I'm going to bring a whole
sheep as an עולה, olah, he said I'll bring like- like a
living sheep as an עולה olah which somehow means the part that
it's needed to live by. Anyway he has a little latitude in
his נדר neder that he- that he gets to- he gets a
checkmark for doing what he needed to do. Okay anyway but that's
what you do. דברי רבי מאיר, Divrei Rabbi Meir, that's what רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir said. רבי יהודה ורבי יוסי ורבי שמעון Rabbi Yehuda
v'Rabbi Yose v'Rabbi Shimon אומרים, omrim, some say- some have the ו'
vav after רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir ורבי יהודה, v'Rabbi Yehuda, it's a
question where you put the
comma. Anyway
רבי יוסי ורבי שמעון Rabbi Yose v'Rabbi Shimon אומרים, omrim, anyway- so
רבי יוסי ורבי שמעון Rabbi Yose v'Rabbi Shimon say מניין, minayin, they
don't agree,
מניין. minayin. So they read the verse other way, anything that even
if you only gave a part of it, ממנו להשם יהיה קודש,
mimenu la-Hashem yiyeh kodesh, the whole thing is holy. Okay, לרבות את
כולה, lerabot et kulah, that everything becomes holy. עולה, Ola, you cannot,
an עולה ola is definitional about the identity. It either is or
it isn't. Like you can't be somewhat pregnant. Okay, you either are
or you're not, so you either are a קרבן korban or you're
not a קרבן. korban. So the גמרא Gemara says, where were we,
לרבות את כולה, lerabot et kulah, ואפילו למאן דאמר אין כולה עולה,
ve-afilu le-man de-amar ein kulah ola, even according to those that say
it can be limited to the leg, הני מילי דאקדיש דבר שאין
נשמה תלויה בו, hani milei de-akdish davar she-ein neshamah teluyah bo, that's
only because it's the leg, it's a non-vital organ. אבל דבר שנשמה
תלויה בו, Aval davar she-neshamah teluyah bo, if it's a vital organ,
קדושה כולה, kedushah kulah, it's all sanctified. So basically we're back to
our problem. We said by ערכין Erchin when you gave it to
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and you said the head, the vital
organ, that it was in entirety. Now we said by a קרבן,
korban, if you say a vital organ, it's the entire thing. What
do you do with this ברייתא braita we quoted yesterday that says
if you said the head that you and the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash are partners?
We've dealt with donations to the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, we've dealt
with קרבנות, korbanot, each one of those a vital organ is the
whole thing. Where are we going to have the case where even
if you said a vital organ, you're only, it's only a partnership
with the בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash? So the גמרא Gemara says, לא
קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא בקדושת הגוף הא בקדושת דמים.
ha bi-kedushat ha-guf ha bi-kedushat damim. It's a question whether it's intrinsic
sanctity or value sanctity. Now let me explain those terms. Those are
very often confused with or made or assumed to be synonymous with
קדושת מזבח kedushat mizbe'ach and קדושת בדק הבית. kedushat bedek ha-bayit. Very
often they are essentially the same thing. Here's קדושת מזבח kedushat mizbe'ach
is for the altar, קדושת בדק הבית kedushat bedek ha-bayit is for
the temple treasury. קדושת הגוף Kedushat ha-guf means you're going to use
the thing itself. קדושת דמים Kedushat damim means you're going to sell
it and use its proceeds. So it would seem that those two
like line up, but they don't have to. I can have something
that I'm going to use the thing itself but isn't a קרבן.
korban. Let's say I donate wood to be used on the מזבח.
mizbe'ach. Let's say I donate a gold vessel to be used as
a כלי שרת. kli sharet. That's a קדושת הגוף kedushat ha-guf without
being קדושת מזבח. kedushat mizbe'ach. I can also have something that is
about its value without being to the temple treasury. What does that
mean? This is a more bizarre case, but I say I am
sanctifying my car for its value, but what I mean by that
is the value, the proceeds of that sale should go to buy
a קרבן. korban. Okay, so that's קדושת דמים למזבח. kedushat damim le-mizbe'ach.
I'm not using the car as a קרבן, korban, I'm using its
proceeds, but the proceeds for the sake of a קרבן. korban. So
קדושת דמים kedushat damim and קדושת הגוף kedushat ha-guf are not the
same as מזבח mizbe'ach and בדק הבית. bedek ha-bayit. So what is
the גמרא's Gemara answer? The גמרא's Gemara answer is, okay, straight to
the temple treasury, vital organ represents the whole thing. Straight for a
קרבן, korban, vital, vital, vital organ
represents the whole thing. If however it's not about the thing directly
being handed over, but it specifically is about using the proceeds for
something else, קדושת דמים, kedushat damim, okay,
so there is and it's for something different than like it's I'm
sanctifying this and the proceeds should go to a קרבן, korban, so
there because it's very much about selling and using the money and
using the money for something else, there we can say vital organ
is not enough to identify the entirety, it means somehow part ownership
by the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. That's how we find this middle
category. Okay, so if I say I'm, even if it's just about
straight money like a straight check to the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash,
then somehow we say vital organ does represent the same thing. So
I say the value of somebody on me to give as a
donation, I say the value of their heart, that represents the whole
thing, I write a check for the whole person. Okay, but if
it's very much about translating the money into some specific purpose for
some reason when you get exactly in between those two categories, proceeds
for a קרבן, korban, that's where saying it's only a partnership. I
cannot really explain it beyond what I just said because to me
I don't really get why just because you're between those two it
should be, it should be, it should be different. But that's at
least what we're saying.
Well, we have something like that in donations today. You can donate
books for a library, for a ישיבה. yeshiva. Right, right. Or you
can give money to the ישיבה. yeshiva.
Right. But the thing is the reason I'm bothered is because one
of the cases where the vital organ represents the whole thing is
where it's not the thing itself, where it still is, if I
say ערך erech of that person's heart עלי, alai, I'm still writing
out a check, right? I'm not giving that person. Or if I
say the market value of that person's heart עלי, alai, right, so
then I am still writing out a check for the whole person.
So there also it's about
money. But if I say the market value of that person's heart
to go towards a קרבן, korban, then I give the value for
half of the person, not the whole person. So why exactly because
I say to go towards... towards a קרבן korban rather than just
to go straight to the בית Beis to the treasury, you know
that becomes evaluated differently is not clear.
Yes, let me just interrupt there for a bit of clarification.
Does it make a distinction whether or not the animal for which
I'm making that statement of
דמי קרבן damei korban is an animal that itself could have been
brought?
Ah, so that's a great point. So that's exactly where the גמרא
Gemara is going to go, and maybe it'll get clarified a little
bit more as we continue. But to this stage we've found a
middle space, but exactly hard to explain why it makes, you know,
how it fully works, but let's keep on going because the גמרא
Gemara is not done.
Is it because you're implicitly entering into a partnership with the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash on that קרבן? korban?
What do you mean? You mean because בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash is
going to get the קרבן, korban, how is it different than when
I say the organ of that slave is, you know, alive, then
I just write a straight check for the whole value?
You're responsible for the-
if I say the organ of that slave to be used towards
a קרבן, korban, then it's half the slave,
because it's the essence of entering into a partnership with the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash which you are implicitly doing by saying it's for
a קרבן korban even though you're not buying a whole קרבן. korban.
Aha.
You mean the קרבן korban has more of a sense of I'm
still sort of engaging the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, you know, along
the whole process, rather than just the writing out of a straight
check. Is that your point?
When you make a donation to the-
it's
more like cut and dry, and then it's not an ongoing relationship.
Right. Is what you're saying. Yeah. All right, I hear. All right,
let's take a look as the גמרא Gemara continues here. So it
says like this: והא מר הוא דאמר, Veha mar hu de'amar, but
now this was רבא Rava who said this, you know, and he
was sort of responding to אביי. Abaye. אביי Abaye was the one
who was challenging רבא. Rava. So now אביי Abaye doesn't like this
answer, but isn't the master- רבא Rava is רבא's Rava master- isn't
the master the one who says מקדיש זכר לדמיו קדוש קדושת הגוף,
makdish zachar l'damav kadosh kedushat haguf,
that you cannot sanctify a male animal that is fit- this is
Mordechai's question- for bringing as a קרבן? korban? If I take a
beautiful
unblemished male sheep, because male you need for an עולה, olah, and
I say I am sanctifying it that the proceeds go to a
קרבן, korban, okay, which is crazy because I could use the thing
itself as an עולה, olah, so basically we get an immediate upgrade.
You're not allowed to do that. It's crazy. Why should we set
aside- it's going to eventually go to a קרבן, korban, you have
to go through the whole thing, since that's where it's headed, we
say it automatically gets upgraded. Okay, wait a minute, so you say
מקדיש זכר לדמיו, makdish zachar l'damav, if you try to sanctify a
male animal for the money, meaning it should be used towards an
עולה- olah that's why it's זכר, zachar, we're assuming עולה- olah קדוש
קדושת הגוף, kadosh kedushat haguf, it automatically gets upgraded. So how can
you even have a scenario where you sanctified an animal, like the
heart, we're talking about an organ, that the money should be used
for a קרבן? korban? Why don't we just- in that case, you
know, it should immediately get upgraded, it should be like sanctifying the
animal directly for a קרבן, korban, where the heart represents the whole
thing? Charles, you have a question.
הקדש Hekdesh loses on that because the cost of a prime wool-producing
sheep
is
far more than an ordinary lamb that you would use for a-
but how do
you- but how do you know that you would- I don't understand,
if you sold this prime wool-producing sheep for, I don't know, a
thousand dollars, and a normal one-day old whatever, eight-day old lamb would
be a hundred dollars. Yeah. You still have to now take this
thousand dollars and use it to buy an עולה. olah. So הקדש
Hekdesh isn't losing. That money, those proceeds have to go- that's what,
why sell the sheep, take the thousand dollars, and now use the
thousand dollars to buy an animal to use as an עולה? olah?
But if I- but if I point
to a wool sheep and
you say זה בדק הבית. zeh bedek habayit. Right.
But you didn't say בדק הבית. bedek habayit. רבא's Rava saying, רבא
Rava said if I say for the sheep- it's not spelled out
here, okay, you're right, but it means you say דמיו לעולה. damav
l'olah. Oh, okay. Yeah.
The context is דמיו לעולה, damav l'olah, right, that's not spelled out.
Okay, so if it's anyway going to an עולה, olah, why go
through the whole rigmarole, just have an automatic upgrade. That's what רבא
Rava says. So if you're saying that the special case here is
when you said the proceeds for a קרבן, korban, you don't have
that middle case, אביי Abaye says to רבא. Rava. According to you,
it always gets upgraded. Now the obvious answer is, oh, it only
gets upgraded if it's unblemished and could be used as a קרבן.
korban. So we're going to get there. But that's the question.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: כי
איבעיא לן- Ki ibaia lan no, רבא Rava says like-
one minute, where are we? והא מר הוא דאמר דאקדיש כולה. Veha
mar hu de'amar de'aktish kulah. So the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא.
lo kashya. Before it gets to the obvious answer that we're talking
about that it's- that it's blemished and can't get upgraded, we're saying
no, here's the difference: לא קשיא הא דאקדיש כולה הא דאקדיש חד
אבר. Lo kashya, ha de'aktish kulah, ha de'aktish chad evar.
The difference is whether you do the whole thing or whether you
do an organ, a vital organ. Meaning, when we say a vital
organ, right, we're saying if you sanctify a vital organ, it's like
you sanctified the whole thing. So we're not going to do a
double translation. I say the lungs of... this sheep, the value towards
an עולה. olah. So in order to make the sheep an עולה,
olah, I have to make a double translation. Lungs means the whole
thing, and even though I said value towards an עולה, olah, I'm
going to upgrade you and make it directly an עולה. olah. So
he's saying I won't do a double translation. I'll do a single
translation. So one minute, the גמרא Gemara says like this. One minute,
הא דאקשי ליה ha d'akshi leh אבר ever נמי nami איבעי ליה
למיבעי. ibaei leh lemibaei.
What do you mean? You've also you also raised that as a
possibility that even when you do a vital organ, it should be
translated as the whole and from there translated as and get an
automatic upgrade? דבעי רבא, debaei Rava, you yourself רבא Rava asked, this
is a גמרא Gemara in תמורה, Temurah, הקדיש אבר לדמיו, hikdish ever
ledamav, I sanctify a vital organ that the proceeds should go to
an עולה, olah, מהו? mahu? What's the story? Does it get upgraded
or not? So we're trying to find a middle space. If you
sanctify an animal straight for a קרבן, korban, a vital organ, it
represents the whole thing. Straight for בדק הבית, Bedek HaBayit, a vital
organ represents the whole thing. We're trying to find a middle space
where vital organ is not the whole thing. We're saying the value
towards a קרבן, korban, but now they're saying you, רבא, Rava, say
that in those cases it automatically becomes a קרבן. korban. You don't
have a middle space. So the גמרא Gemara says, ah, so here
it's going to finally get the answer that we would have expected.
כי בעי לן, ki baei lan, when was our question that or
that might be even an organ gets translated as the whole gets
automatically upgraded? בתם, betam, when it's unblemished, when it could become a
קרבן korban itself. הכא בבעל מום, hacha bebaal mum, here we're talking
about a blemish. ודומיא דחמור, udumya d'chamor, because remember the ברייתא baraita
we quoted yesterday, which gave the case where it was not the
whole thing, where when you said the whole or vital organ you
were partners, that it said a donkey, a slave, so we're not
just
talking about things that can get upgraded, that can become a קרבן.
korban. So even when we talk about a cow and a sheep,
we're talking about them that they cannot be them themselves become קרבנות.
korbanot. So now we have to figure out how to inhabit the
middle space, and this maybe explains also better a little bit why
again why you're partner. If you give straight a donation to the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, I'll give the value of the slave's heart,
so you give the value of the whole slave. If you give
straight to a קרבן, korban, I'll give the
I'm sanctifying this sheep's heart, the whole sheep is קדוש. kadosh. If
you're saying the value of the sheep's heart towards a קרבן, korban,
or the slave's heart towards a קרבן, korban, you're in this middle
space and you can't get an upgrade because the sheep has a
blemish and the slave can't be a קרבן korban or the donkey
or whatever. In those cases, we actually consider it to be more
of a partnership and not the entire thing. So we've managed once
again to inhabit this middle space. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
continues. Wait, who says this?
And what's the point where we decide that אבר ever meant a
vital organ?
Based on just the context of the גמרא Gemara before, because it
contracted it to רגלו. reglo. Okay, but yeah, it's not explicit. It's
based on context. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like that. I
mean, look, according to the position that said רגלו reglo would be
כולו קדוש, kulo kadosh, it wouldn't be limited to vital organ. But
vital organ everybody agrees on. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
the following.
And besides, the whole notion of אבר ever being an organ at
all was...
Right, right. So it's based on the debate of תנאים Tannaim before.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, והא דאקשי ליה, veha
d'akshi leh, so the גמרא Gemara says בבעל מום נמי איבעי ליה
למיבעי. bebaal mum nami ibaei leh lemibaei. One minute, you can't get
out of that, because you רבא Rava yourself said that even by
a בעל מום baal mum maybe it gets an upgrade. You're not
going to bring this as a קרבן, korban, but maybe it gets
קדושת קרבן. kedushat korban. דבעי רבא, debaei Rava, you yourself asked over
there in תמורה, Temurah, דמי ראשי לגבי מזבח, demei roshi legabei mizbei'ach,
מהו? mahu?
Now this is obviously not an upgrade for a קרבן, korban, because
you're talking about yourself. You say the value of my head would
be now used for a קרבן. korban. So nobody's saying that you
become a קרבן. korban. But the question that you were asking there
was exactly the question we've had, which is when you are saying
value of a vital organ, the proceeds to be used towards a
קרבן, korban, do you value based on the entire person or the
entire thing if it's a or just on or part or partial?
So now we have inhabited this middle space, but we're saying רבא,
Rava, one minute, you yourself רבא Rava said you don't know how
to deal with that middle case. When you say the value of
the vital organ towards a קרבן, korban, is it partial or is
it full? You raise the question, but we have a ברייתא baraita
before that very clearly said partial. So how are we going to
deal with this? So the גמרא Gemara says, כי בעי לן, ki
baei lan, okay,
you're right. You know what? When רבא Rava raised the question, when
we raised that question מקמי דאשמעה להמתניתא, mikamei d'ashma'ah lehamatnita, it was
before we heard this ברייתא. baraita. השתא דאשמעה להמתניתא, hashta d'ashma'ah lehamatnita,
now that we've been informed of this ברייתא, baraita, which we taught
yesterday, fine, לא מיבעי לן, lo mibaei lan, thank you very much,
you helped me resolve my question. Okay, so that was
very arduous, but basically what we have said, straight to the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, straight to a קרבן, korban, vital organ is the
whole thing. If it is this middle hybrid category, the value of
this vital organ towards a קרבן, korban, then it might then we
have a ברייתא baraita that tells us that's only half and half,
it is not the whole thing. Now we wrap up this סוגיא
sugya with a couple of other hybrid cases, and let's take a
look. So בעי
רבא, baei Rava, רבא Rava asked, גופו, gufo,
let's go back to this original... to what we just quoted. בעי
רבא, baei Rava, רבא Rava asked, מראש לי לגבי מזבח, meirosh lee
legabi mizbeach,
the value of my head towards the altar, okay, which is basically
a vital organ, so do I now owe money and now the
money's used for a קרבן, korban, am I so מהו, mahu, what's
the story? Does is it the full value of me towards a
קרבן, korban, only half the value of me? נידון בכבודו או אינו
נידון בכבודו? niddon bichvodo o eino niddon bichvodo? Do we say we
do the that it's judged by my כבודו, kvodo, my honor, meaning
it represents my entirety and my entire value goes now towards a
קרבן? korban? או אינו נידון בכבודו, o eino niddon bichvodo, or not?
It's only partial based on the ברייתא. braita. Now this was again
before we had the ברייתא. braita. Before we know the answer now
based on the ברייתא braita is that this is the one exception,
it's only half and half. But let's understand what his question was
just as a theoretical question. Do we say לא אשכחן בדמים דאינו
נידון בכבודו? lo ashkachan bidamim deaino niddon bichvodo? We know when it
comes to donation value sanctity, that that the part represents the whole,
that's what we learned from ערכין, erchin, that if you say the
ערך erech of this person's lungs or heart is on me, you
pay the whole value. So we know that when you're dealing with
money value, when valuation, it goes by the entirety. So that would
say that this should go by the entirety. או דילמא, o dilma,
or do we say לא אשכחן לגבי מזבח דנידון בכבודו? lo ashkachan
legabi mizbeach deniddon bichvodo? When it comes to the altar, you don't
go by the entirety. Now again, that's not really fully true, because
if you directly sanctify something for the altar, the heart of this
sheep is an עולה, olah, the whole sheep is an עולה. olah.
But it means we've never found the hybrid money going towards a
קרבן. korban. Direct קרבן, korban, yes, it's we go כבודו, kvodo, meaning
organ represents the entire entirety. Direct donation to the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, organ entirety. But where the money goes towards a קרבן, korban,
that's a middle case, maybe it does not go that way. תיקו.
teiku. The גמרא Gemara says we don't know the answer. Now that,
when it was asked as a theoretical question with no evidence, was
left as a question, but now the גמרא Gemara said we have
a ברייתא braita that actually says it is an exception, it's only
when it's fully one or fully the other. When it's this hybrid
case, it is split, you and the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, not
fully to the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, so that was that
case. One or two more hybrid cases. בעי רבא. baei Rava. רבא
Rava asked, how was this
case different
from the ברייתא braita case? It's not. The גמרא Gemara said a
minute ago that this was only raised before we had the ברייתא.
braita. So when it was raised just as a סברא sevara question,
we didn't have a good way to answer it. Now we're going
to answer now we've answered it now that we have the ברייתא.
braita. Okay, that's the hybrid case. Now we're going to have one
or two other hybrid cases. בעי רבא. baei Rava. Now we have
רבא Rava being the one to ask. There's a question throughout this
if the גירסא girsa is רבא Rava or רבה. Rabbah. Anyway. ערכי
עלי לגבי מזבח, erchi alai legabi mizbeach, מהו? mahu? Here's another type
of a flip. We said that I'm going to use the money
from the proceeds for the מזבח, mizbeach, fine. Let but the word
ערכי erchi when I use that magic word ערכי erchi which goes
by the charts in the Torah, that's always understood to mean a
donation to the Temple treasury. Let's say I try to draw on
that system but to use it for a קרבן. korban. I say,
"I will pay my ערך erech to use for an עולה." olah.
So do I go by the charts in the Torah? Male, female,
age, etc. Okay, that those charts were intended when it's a donation
to the Temple treasury, right? So how what will I do with
this hybrid case which we've never really, you know, acknowledged before? Okay,
so ערכי עלי לגבי מזבח, erchi alai legabi mizbeach, מהו? mahu? So
here's the way רבא Rava raises the question. נידון בהשיג יד או
אינו נידון בהשיג יד? niddon behaseig yad o eino niddon behaseig yad?
Do we allow you to when you do a straight case of
ערכין, erchin, you could have asked an earlier question, do we even
go by the charts in the Torah? But רבא Rava is saying
it differently. Do we do we allow it to be a sliding
scale, right? We talked yesterday השיג יד haseig yad that the Torah
says that it's based on what the person can afford. There's fixed
values, but if you can't afford it, it's a sliding scale. So
if you use the system of ערכין, erchin, but not for a
Temple donation but for a קרבן, korban, would we apply the rules
of ערכין erchin and allow for a sliding scale if you can't
afford the fixed value? Do we say לא אשכחן בערכין דאין נידון
בהשיג יד? lo ashkachan beerchin deein niddon behaseig yad? Once you're using
the system of ערכין, erchin, that we never find that you don't
have a sliding scale, so obviously we'd need to give you a
sliding scale. או דילמא, o dilma, or do we say לא אשכחן
לגבי מזבח דמשתקיל אלא בשוויה? lo ashkachan legabi mizbeach demishtakeil ela beshavyei?
When you do a donation to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash for
a קרבן, korban, we never have a sliding scale, it's always the
exact amount. So you've tried to create a hybrid, ערכין erchin for
a קרבן. korban. So do we give you rules of ערכין erchin
or do we give you rules of קרבן? korban? Do we allow
for a sliding scale? Okay, now again, it is interesting that he
assumes that we would go by the fixed values in the Torah
and the only question is sliding scale, right? You could have said
maybe we don't even do that, the Torah only acknowledges ערכין erchin
for for a Temple donation. But he presumably says no, that's at
least clear that you meant whatever explicitly we'll translate your words as,
whatever value the Torah would have assigned for ערכין, erchin, that's the
value I'm obligating myself as a קרבן. korban. So we can translate
your words that way, but maybe since it's not real ערכין, erchin,
we don't allow you the benefit of the sliding scale. That was
his question. One last hybrid case. בעי רב אשי, baei Rav Ashi,
רב אשי Rav Ashi asked, what was the answer? Don't know. תיקו.
teiku. Okay.
People are trying to create weird animals so we don't know how
to deal with them. Okay. בעא רב אשי: Baei Rav Ashi: הקדיש
שדה אחוזה לגבי מזבח. hikdish sdei achuza legabei mizbe'ach.
I sanctified my field, my the field that I've inherited, right, my
you know, that has come down to me from you know from
שבט ראובן Shevet Reuven and I'm descendants of ראובן. Reuven. It's my
שדה אחוזה sdei achuza and normally the תורה Torah says if I
sanctify it for the temple treasury, then there's a specific way in
which I can redeem it in the years leading up to the
יובל Yovel based on again a fixed value that the תורה Torah
assigns. Let's say I sanctify it but not to the temple treasury,
that the proceeds of the sale will go to buy קרבנות. korbanot.
Okay, so again I've made this weird hybrid. Do I—am I allowed
the special rules of how to redeem it that the תורה Torah
assigns for when I sanctify it for the temple treasury? מי אמרינן,
Mi amrinan, do we say לא אשכחן שדה אחוזה דמפרקא אלא בבית
זרע חומר שעורים בחמישים שקל כסף? lo ashkechan sdei achuza demiparka ela
beveit zera chomer seorim bachamishim shekel kesef? That the way you redeem
a field of inheritance is that based on בית זרע חומר שעורים,
beit zera chomer seorim, based on quoting the פסוק, pasuk, בית זרע
חומר שעורים, beit zera chomer seorim, based on the amount that's planted
by a certain amount of barley for each acre let's say or
whatever that amount is, 50 שקל, shekel, there's a fixed way in
which to redeem it and therefore since this is a שדה אחוזה
sdei achuza and it was sanctified, it goes by that fixed value
in the תורה? Torah? או דילמא, O dilma, or do we say
לא אשכחן לגבי מזבח דמפרקא אלא בשוויה? lo ashkechan legabei mizbe'ach demiparka
ela beshavya? That when you sanctify something for the altar, so altar
is by its fixed its market value? So what do you do
with this hybrid where it's on the one hand a שדה אחוזה
sdei achuza but on the other hand for the altar? Do you
go by the fixed value, the market value? תיקו, Teiku, we don't
know. Couple people that are trying to create weird mixed categories, but
you understand the reason, maybe it's worth pointing out again, the reason
that we can have these weird mixed categories is because the גמרא
Gemara allows for a concept of קדושת דמים לגבי מזבח. kedushat damim
legabei mizbe'ach. That logically I understand, I mean when I told you,
you know that these categories, מזבח mizbe'ach and בדק הבית bedek habayit
and גוף guf and דמים damim are not exactly the same. We
can all understand the natural category of sanctifying something for direct use
that isn't a קרבן. korban. Wood for the altar, a vessel for
the בדק הבית. bedek habayit. I don't think we would have assumed
that you could say I'm sanctifying my car that the money gets
used towards a קרבן. korban. We might have assumed that if you
want to sanctify a קרבן, korban, you only have to sanctify the
animal directly. You can't sanctify something for money to go towards a
קרבן. korban. Once the גמרא Gemara allows for that, דמים למזבח, damim
lemizbe'ach, money proceeds for a קרבן, korban, then that allows for these
very weird hybrids. So these weird hybrids are almost an outgrowth of
saying that there is this category called money for a קרבן. korban.
So now we want to know what happens if you try to
create hybrids, you know, using תורה Torah categories. Okay, so we leave
those questions basically unanswered. Now we're able to put that very complicated
סוגיא sugya aside and go to something much more straightforward, back to
normal issues of ערכין. Erchin. Let's look at the next משנה. mishna.
פחות מבן חודש נידר אבל לא נערך. Pachot miben chodesh nidar aval
lo ne'erach. Less than a month old, right, is not in the
תורה's Torah's category of
ערכין. Erchin. That starts with babies that are one month old and
higher, the fixed values, but it is נידר. nidar. If you say
that I will pay the market value for it, not the ערך,
erech, the fixed value, then obviously even though it's not in ערכין,
Erchin, you go by whatever the market value is. That's what you
said. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן: Tanu
rabanan: המעריך פחות מבן חודש. hame'areich pachot miben chodesh. Let's say you
did—you actually said I will pay the ערך erech of this infant,
this less than one month old infant. You said ערך erech which
the תורה Torah does not recognize. רבי מאיר אומר נותן דמיו: Rabbi
Meir omer noten damav: you pay the market value even though you
said ערך. erech. וחכמים אומרים לא אמר כלום: vachachamim omrim lo amar
klum: you didn't say anything. ערך erech of this—what's the ערך erech
of a less than one month old? Zero. So he pays zero.
במאי קמיפלגי? Bemai kamipalgi? What's the debate, meaning really what's רבי מאיר's
Rabbi Meir logic? If you said ערך erech and why are you
paying market value? רבי מאיר סבר אין אדם מוציא דבריו לבטלה. Rabbi
Meir savar ein adam motzi devarav levatala. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
people don't just say stupid nonsense statements. So if you said ערך,
erech, you probably meant something else. Okay, so therefore, יודע שאין ערך
לפחות מבן חודש. yode'a she'ein erech lepachot miben chodesh. We assume that
you know that there's no ערך erech for less than one month
old. וגמר ואמר לשם דמים. vegamur ve'amar leshem damim. So what you
really mean to be saying is not the ערך, erech, you really
mean to be saying market value. It's true, before any of you
started learning דף יומי, Daf Yomi, who would have thought there's a
difference if I say ערך erech or דמים? damim? That one means
a fixed value and one means a market value. So if you
said ערך, erech, presumably you meant the market value. That's what רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says. Now תוספות Tosafot says even if you don't
know, even if you haven't been going to the דף יומי Daf
Yomi and you don't know the difference between ערך erech and דמים,
damim, we will interpret your word that way. Basically, we will assume
that you want your words to be meaningful and they should have
whatever meaning makes them meaningful, and therefore in this context, we'll give
it the meaning of market value because when you say something, you
want it to be meaningful to have whatever meaning can be effective.
That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. והרבנן סברי, Veharabanan savrei, the
Rabbis hold אדם מוציא דבריו לבטלה, adam motzi devarav levatala, we're prepared
to say that you say nonsense statements, we'll only go by what
you actually said. Now תוספות, Tosafot, I should point out because if
people read my blog introduction to ערכין Erchin about how much of
this is based on your דעת, da'at, so תוספות Tosafot actually— He
says according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who cares if what we
think you wouldn't want your words to be meaningless blah blah. You
said ערך ערכך, erekh erkha, we should go by what you said
and the ערך erekh of this infant is zero. So תוספות Tosafot
points out, no, that's exactly the point that when you deal with
ערכין, erkhin, we do care very much about what you're thinking and
not just about what you've said. So therefore רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir
prepared to say that if I'm going to assume people want their
words to be meaningful, even if it's not exactly what you said,
I will interpret your words accordingly. Okay? And תוספות Tosafot actually said
it's easier to do in this case. If somebody says something that's
a complete error, they wanted to say, you know,
this man's ערך erekh and by accident they said the woman's ערך,
erekh, they made something which was a complete error and therefore what
they said isn't what they were thinking, we throw it out. But
here it's not a complete error, here it's a translating of the
term. When you say ערך erekh in this context, you meant דמים.
damim. So it wasn't like a complete error. Complete error would be
where you'd say your thoughts and your words don't match, it's all
thrown out. And again, because by הפלאה hafla'ah we care about what
you're thinking, not just what you said. But when it's not a
complete error, it's a question about contextual meaning, then רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says we can use what we're thinking, what we would assume
you're thinking, to determine what those terms mean. So the point though
being here that again, we're able to do this because we're able
to care more, or we do care more here about what you're
thinking, not just about what you said.
Yes. למעשה L'maaseh it will become clear through his actions since he's
the one who said it, he's the one
who has to do it. Right.
So what is the נפקא מינא להלכה nafka mina l'halakha despite that
we're going to give it a...
Well, if somebody just סתם stam wants to write the check, that's
fine. But let's say after the person said it, you know, I
don't know, he said, you know what, I changed my mind, I
really don't have the money, whatever. I mean, you know, there's whatever,
there's scenarios where you still want to know bottom line. If obviously
he's going to write the check, he'll write the check, who cares.
But the question is, do we assume that there is this obligation
now and that then he can be imposed upon him or, you
know, even
a statement like 'I changed my mind' is an indication that his
דעת daas at the time was for...
Right. So that's in general a question here, which is if we
care about דעת, daas, how much do we trust your own reporting
about what your דעת daas is? How do we know what your
דעת daas is? I'm not going to get into that. That's a
good question. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir here is just saying, I'm not
even going to ask you. I'm assuming when people say things, they
meant it to be meaningful and I will interpret it accordingly. Okay,
let's keep on going. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, כמאן
אזלא הא דאמר רב גידל? keman azla ha d'amar Rav Gidel? How
does it go that which we said in the name of רב
גידל? Rav Gidel? אמר
רב, Amar Rav, האומר ערך כלי עלי, ha'omer erekh kli alai, the
ערך, erekh, again, that magic word ערך erekh which refers to those
fixed values in the תורה, Torah, of this vessel, the ערך erekh
of my car, I'll pay to the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So
נותן דמים, noten damim, you give the market value. Because you could
have said, well, let's look, the תורה Torah ערכין erkhin doesn't have
cars, you pay zero. So no, it's that you actually use the
market value. Who's that going like? To רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Like
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that says if ערך erekh doesn't work, then
what we'll assume you meant was דמים damim market value. By the
way, you know in modern Hebrew, right, ערך erekh is just straight
value. Obviously it doesn't have that limited technical terminology. That's actually interesting
because ערכים arakhim actually means values, like you know, like not value
like money values, like the values we hold dear. So ערכים arakhim
now in modern Hebrew. But anyway, here in halakhic literature, it has
a technical term. But רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you might misuse
that technical term, therefore I'll interpret it more broadly. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says פשיטא pshita obviously דרבי מאיר היא. de'Rabbi Meir hi.
It's going like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. He's the one that gives
that meaning to ערך erekh if you have to. No, מהו דתימא
mahu d'tema I might have thought אפילו כרבנן, afilu keRabbanan, maybe even
the Rabbis would agree. התם הוא דטעי, Hatam hu d'ta'ei, סבר, sevar,
there he makes a mistake. He, meaning in our
משנה, Mishnah, כהי דאיכא ערכין בן חודש, ke'hei de'ika erkhin ben chodesh,
איכא נמי לפחות מבן חודש. ika nami lephachot miben chodesh. Maybe you
really don't know, meaning you know the word ערך erekh means the
technical term, but maybe you honestly think you've never, you know, you
don't pay attention whether that part of the פרשה, Parsha, right, because
it's whatever, it's not narrative, it's not as interesting to you, so
therefore you assume that there was an ערך erekh to less than
a בן חודש. ben chodesh. So therefore if it was a mistake,
so then you really didn't mean to obligate yourself in anything. And
therefore in the משנה Mishnah you're exempt because you made a real
mistake. אבל הכא, Aval hacha, here, by a כלי, kli, דליכא למידי,
delika lemidi, nobody is stupid enough to think that the word ערך
erekh refers to a vessel. וודאי אדם יודע שאין ערך לכלי, Vadai
adam yodea she'ein erekh likli, you certainly must know that. וגמר ואמר
לשון דמים, Vegamar ve'amar leshun damim, and therefore in this case we'll
assume that you actually did mean it in the broader sense as
market value. קמשמע לן Kamashmalan we don't say that. Meaning maybe the
Rabbis in principle agree to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that we'd like
to interpret your statement meaningfully, but they say there are some times
where we honestly think you made a mistake. And those things we'll
reject. קמשמע לן Kamashmalan that's not true, that the Rabbis will always
interpret your what you said
based on literally what came out of your mouth, and ערך erekh
they'll interpret technically, and therefore if you said ערך erekh where it
doesn't apply, you're not obligated in anything. Okay. So, רבי מאיר,
Rabbi
Meir, what? Where did from this whole discussion that
there was this whole...
Well, that question,
I don't know if there's inflation, right, presumably, right, we've never really
explored that, where are those values in the Torah coming from? Presumably,
you know, they are coming from, I would, one would guess, although,
that they are coming from some type of, like, standard market value
based on the slave trade. One would guess that's where it's coming
from, which would explain, by the way, why it's, I think actually
a little bit more satisfying to say that because it explains why
the men are always valued more than the women, rather than treating
that as some type of existential, you know, statement, you know, but
as in the slave market, men had a higher value because they
could do more... And if you want to make more slaves... Yeah,
but that's maybe particularly, you know, but I
understand,
but I actually do think, I'm sure we could find out, there's
plenty of information about this, and I'm pretty sure that this is
actually the fact: that the only women that were really highly valued
were the very attractive ones that the slave owners wanted to use
for sexual purposes. Okay, but not just to produce babies. But, you
know, but anyway... I understand. Anyways, anyways, yes, it is probably the
case that those values are somewhat corresponding to a standard market value.
But again, doesn't estimate inflation or deflation. A standard market value does
not take case-by-case into consideration. Okay, let's keep on going.
Yes, you said according to Rabbi Meir that if you said your
car, you'd pay the market value, but then the conclusion was what?
That the opposite...
No, that even maybe the rabbis would even agree to that case.
They would agree. But the answer is no, the rabbis don't, that
is also part of the debate. Right. And they disagree with Rabbi
Meir. And now the Gemara continues, למאי איצטריך? l'mai itzterach? So okay,
but shouldn't that at least if you're saying it's only going according
to Rabbi Meir, then isn't it obvious? If you say the ערך
erech of a infant means the market value, certainly the ערך erech
of a car means the market value. No. מהו דתימא, ma d'teima,
I might have thought Rabbi Meir is based on a different principle,
not that he wants to always interpret your words meaningfully, but maybe
it's just based on a rabbinic safeguard. טעמא דרבי מאיר, taama d'Rabbi
Meir, the reason of Rabbi Meir in our Mishnah is not because
he's generally tries to give meaning to your words. Here's the reason
of Rabbi Meir. התם דגזר פחות מבן חודש אטו בן חודש. hasam
d'gazar pahot mibven hodesh atu ben hodesh. He forces people to pay
by less than a month because not everybody knows exactly under month,
more than a month, and if you get off in under a
month, people will come to not pay even when it's more than
a month. So maybe it's just a rabbinic safeguard, not a basic
principle of interpreting your words meaningfully. אבל
הכא דליכא למיגזר, aval hacha d'leika l'migzar, here by a vessel where
there's nothing to confuse with, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe he'll let
you get off. קא משמע לן kamashma lan that it's not based
on a safeguard. טעמא דרבי מאיר, taama d'Rabbi Meir, his reason is
a principled position דאין אדם מוציא דבריו לבטלה, d'ein adam motzi devarav
l'vattala, that we assume you do not say meaningless statements and therefore
we are going to interpret your words to mean some to be
meaningful. לא שנא הכא ולא שנא הכא, lo shna hacha v'lo shna
hacha, it doesn't matter by an infant, it doesn't matter by a
vessel, you might say ערך, erech, but if it doesn't work in
the technical sense, we'll interpret it in a non-technical way to make
to make it that your statement is meaningful. Okay. So now the
Gemara wraps this up. כמאן אזלא הא דאמר רבה בר רב יוסף
אמר רב אמרי לה אמר רב ייבא בר יוסף אמר רב. k'man
azla had'amar Rabba bar Rav Yosef amar Rav, amri lei amar Rav
Yeiva bar Yosef amar Rav. So who is this going like, this
statement in the name of Rav? המקדיש בהמת חבירו נותן דמיה. hamakdish
behemot chaveiro nosein dameha.
I go and I say, oh James, I am sanctifying your cow.
Now I can't sanctify your cow. It's my it's not it's his
cow, it's not mine. We interpret that to mean I'm going to
donate the value of your cow to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
That's a pretty big stretch, right? It's one thing to say ערך
erech doesn't have the narrow technical meaning of ערך, erech, it just
means market value. It's another thing to say I'm sanctifying your cow
means I'm giving to הקדש Hekdesh the value of your cow. But
that is a statement, so who is that going
like? Obviously כמאן, k'man, who's that going like? To Rabbi Meir. So
the Gemara says הא אמרה רב חדא זימנא, ha amrah Rav chada
zimna,
didn't we have already implicitly know this from Rav? דאמר רב גידל
אמר רב האומר ערך כלי עלי נותן דמיו. d'amar Rav Gidel amar
Rav ha'omer erech kli alai nosein damav. The ערך erech of a
vessel, you give the market value. Again, I think this is a
much bigger חידוש. chiddush. There it's just saying the word ערך erech
doesn't have a narrow technical meaning. Here it's a much bigger reinterpretation
of the statement. So let's see what the Gemara says. מהו דתימא,
ma d'teima, I might have thought התם הוא דידע דאין ערך לכלי.
hasam hu d'yada d'ein erech l'kli. I know that there is no
ערך erech fixed value for the כלי kli based on the Torah.
וגמר ואמר לשם דמים. v'gamar v'amar l'shem damim. So ערך erech will
be mean when I say ערך, erech, what I really mean, or
the way we interpret what I mean is market value. אבל בהמה
דבר הקדש היא, aval behema d'bar hakdash hi, but
an animal that really can be sanctified. So when I say I'm
sanctifying it, it's a big stretch to say that what that means
is I'm giving the value to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So
how else would we interpret what I say to be somewhat meaningful?
Maybe here's how I would have interpreted. איכא למימר דהכי קאמר, ika
l'meimar d'hachi ka'amar,
maybe here's what I mean. אי אמינא ליה למרא מזבין ליה ניהלי,
iy amina lei l'marei mazbin lei nili, if I'm able to tell
the master to sell it to me, I'm able to buy it
off and קנייה, k'neih, תקדש מהשתא ואקרביה, tikdesh meihashta v'akrevih, then I
want to sanctify it and bring it as a קרבן. korban. So
meaning yes, we want to reinterpret what you mean, but we would
more likely try to reinterpret. within the context of what you said.
So if I'm saying I'm sanctifying that animal to give it any
type of a meaning what we might be saying is I'm committing
myself to to try to buy the animal from James and then
to sanctify it and bring it as a קרבן. korban. Maybe that's
how I would have interpreted, maybe not in a way that actually
makes it binding right now because that's very ten, you know, that's
very
tenuous that that will actually succeed. And the גמרא Gemara so the
גמרא Gemara says so אלא אמר דמי לא קאמר alla amar d'mei
lo ka'amar but you don't really need to obligate yourself from the
money right because that's a big stretch from those words קמשמע לן
kamashma lan that רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir goes so far to say
that I want to give meaning to your words, halakhic meaning, that
I will really stretch what you said in order to make it
that you said something that's halakhically meaningful. Okay, now I should say
by the way that although תוספות Tosafot says that this is based
on our ability to get into what you're thinking and not what
you said because ערך erech and whatever is based on what you're
thinking, it seems that this is going beyond that, that in the
end of the day I'm probably not thinking anything like this and
it seems that maybe it's even a more formalistic type of of
an approach of רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir which is, you know, like
a legal position which is we're going to assume statements are legally
binding and therefore we're going to give them an interpretation that makes
them so because here it's a real stretch to say that that's
what I was thinking.
Can you make a נדר neder on something that doesn't exist at
that moment?
To sanctify it?
No, I mean in other words
to obligate yourself to pay
for it somehow?
Yes. To obligate yourself to pay its value? Yes. Because then it's
just really saying I owe X amount to the בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash. But to sanctify it, to give it still sanctity in it
as an object? No. It has to exist and it has to
be mine. So that's why we can't give meaning to your word,
like the fetus of a pregnant animal.
Right. So now the גמרא Gemara says because this is such a
stretch, the גמרא Gemara qualifies it a little. אמר רב אשי amar
Rav Ashi והוא דאמר עלי. v'hu d'amar alai.
I have to give you some hook to hang on. If I
said I'm sanctifying James' cow, I'm sorry, you can't say that that
means I have to pay money to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
If I say I am sanctifying רש״י Rashi gives the phrase, רש״י
Rashi says בהמת חבירו זו עלי, behemas chaveiro zu alai, James' cow
is on me as a קרבן. korban. So that already, I mean
that's not exactly what we said before, that already sounds much more
like an obligation than a sanctification. So even though it sounds like
I'm obligating myself to bring it as a קרבן korban if I
buy it from James or whatever, since at least there I said
is on me, I can say what it means is I'm obligating
myself in its value. והוא דאמר עלי v'hu d'amar alai אבל אמר
הרי זו aval amar harei zu if you said I'm this animal
is a קרבן, korban, whoa, that much we can't stretch your words.
Okay, so here you get basically רבי מאיר׳ס Rebbi Meir's position, the
rabbis say I will do technically with what you said, רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir says I will try to interpret what you said to
be meaningful. תוספות Tosafot basically says that it's based on our concern
with what you're thinking, although maybe רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir is more
just a general points out just just
legally I'm going to assume your words are binding and find a
way to make them so. Anyway, but in the case is in
the initial cases it was a very simple reinterpretation. ערך Erech doesn't
have a narrow technical sense, it has more of a vernacular sense
of market value. There was then an attempt to explain it much
more broadly to go from sanctifying to creating it an an obligation
to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and the גמרא Gemara then tried
to pull back on that and try to get it a little
bit closer to the words you actually said.
Is there being punitive like you?
I don't think so. I think look, in general you have people...
Yeah, look look, you have a lot of great cases where it's
interesting to try to pull the רבי מאירס Rebbi Meirs together about
what what רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir does with language, his positions about
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir do we say מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן
miklal lav ata shomeiah hein or not, when you say the positive
to reinforce the negative. There's questions about let's say somebody says contradictory
words, he says הרי זו עולה שלמים. harei zu olah shelamim. So
do we assume that you made the animal a hybrid עולה שלמים
olah shelamim or do we assume that your word שלמים shelamim was
a you were correcting yourself? So it would be interesting I don't
think it's punitive, I think there's a question about how much do
we try to interpret things to make them fit within the system
as contextual or how much do we take a very sort of
literal read of everything that you've said. So there's it's linked to
a couple of different things. So people who want to do a
little project for independent study, if you want to do a paper
on it but I'm serious, רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir has a couple
of interesting positions around those types of things.
Is there any enforcement of any kind with that?
Interestingly we are going to get to ערכין Erchin and ערכין Erchin
is a very interesting מסכת Masechet because it deals with how בית
דין Beis Din actually, both when you have obligations of קרבנות korbanos
and other obligations, can actually seize your property and compel you to
satisfy your religious or your financial obligations. So yeah, so we will
get to all of that. Let's take a look at the next
משנה. mishna. עובדי כוכבים, Ovedei kochavim,
how about a non-Jew? We dealt with less than a month old.
How about a non-Jew, right? The תורה Torah says male or female,
what's the story if I try to say the value of that
the ערך erech of that non-Jew? Do I go by the charts
or not? So רבי מאיר אומר, Rebbi Meir omer, רבי מאיר. Rebbi
Meir. he says נערך, ne'erach, he is on those charts. Those charts
are about male, female. We might exclude mixed gender, but we're not
excluding non-Jews, never said those charts were limited to Jews, אבל לא
מעריך. aval lo maarich. He's not in the category of obligating himself.
If a non-Jew says my, the ערך erech of so-and-so is on
me to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, and he somehow is listening
to us and wants to do what our legal system tells him,
but Rabbi Meir says that would not be binding on him. Okay.
Not great policy if you're trying to increase your revenues for the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer,
Rabbi Yehuda
says מעריך, maarich, he can donate, אבל לא נערך, aval lo ne'erach,
but he's not an object if you sort of, if you obligate
yourself to pay the value of a non-Jew. Donations we'll take from
anyone. Okay? You can be מעריך, maarich, but he's not
נערך. ne'erach. וזה וזה מודים, Vezeh vezeh modim, both agree, and here's
interesting, שנודרים ונידרים. shenodrim venidrim. All of this is a question in
this technical category of ערכין. erechin. But if the non-Jew just says
סתם, stam, I'm going to donate a thousand dollars to the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, very nice, welcome. Or if you say, I will
give the market value of the non-Jew to the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, you pay. So if you're dealing with just simple donations, market
values, those types of things, everybody agrees he can be obligate himself
to give and he can be the object of such. The only
question is in the technical category of ערך. erech. Which role does
he play? One, but not the other. Let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. So
the פרשה parsha of ערכין erechin begins with דבר אל בני ישראל.
dabeir el Bnei Yisrael. So speak to the children of Israel. So
that's הוה אמינא, hava amina, this is limited to Jews. In what
way is it limited to Jews? So that's the debate. בני ישראל
מעריכין ואין עובדי כוכבים מעריכין, Bnei Yisrael maarichin ve'ein ovdei kochavim maarichin,
only Jews can obligate themselves in ערך, erech, not non-Jews. יכול לא
יהיו נערכין, Yachol lo yiheyu ne'erachin, maybe the non-Jews cannot be the
object of ערכין, erechin, if you you know, if you say the
value of that non-Jew, the ערך erech of that non-Jew? תלמוד לומר
איש. Talmud lomar ish. It says a man. So therefore it's about
being male or female and it's not in terms of being on
the charts. דברי רבי מאיר. Divrei Rabbi Meir. That's what Rabbi Meir
says. אמר רבי מאיר. Amar Rabbi Meir. Did I see, אמר רבי
מאיר? amar Rabbi Meir?
He explains himself. Meir says look, one verse is inclusive, says איש,
ish,
another verse is exclusive, בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. מפני מה אני אומר
נערך ולא מעריך? Mipnei mah ani omer ne'erach velo maarich?
Why do I say that he is נערך, ne'erach, he can be
the object of an ערך, erech, but he cannot be the מעריך,
maarich, the person making the ערך? erech? מפני שריבה כתוב בנערכים יותר
מבמעריכים. Mipnei sheribah kasuv bene'erachim yoseir mibemaarichin.
Because there are more people on the charts of the נערכים, ne'erachim,
the objects, than those that can make an ערך. erech. Who's what
does that mean? שהרי חרש שוטה וקטן נערך. Sheharei cheireish shoteh vekatan
ne'erach. You can be somebody who does not have דעת, da'as, a
חרש שוטה וקטן, cheireish shoteh vekatan, and you can still be the
object of an ערך. erech. You're still on those charts. אבל לא
מעריכין, Aval lo maarichin, but they cannot be the subject. So similarly
by a non-Jew. A non-Jew is and in a way there's a
certain intuitive sense to this, right? Because since he's not so much
as part of our system, so he can't as much be an
actor in the system. But to be on the charts, there you're
basically turning people into objects, not into actors. So there you can
do it for a non-the same you can do it for a
חרש שוטה וקטן, cheireish shoteh vekatan, do it for a non-Jew. That's
what Rabbi Meir says. רבי יהודה אומר. Rabbi Yehuda omer. Rabbi Yehuda
says בני ישראל נערכין ואין עובדי כוכבים נערכין. Bnei Yisrael ne'erachin ve'ein
ovdei kochavim ne'erachin. The reverse. בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael are on the
charts, not non-Jews. יכול לא יהיו מעריכין, Yachol lo yiheyu maarichin, maybe
non-Jews should not be able to be making an ערך? erech? תלמוד
לומר איש, Talmud lomar ish, a man, anybody. אמר רבי יהודה. Amar
Rabbi Yehuda. So now Rabbi Yehuda has to explain his position. מפני
מה אני אומר עובדי כוכבים מעריך ולא נערך? Mipnei mah ani omer
ovdei kochavim maarich velo ne'erach? Since one is inclusive and one is
limited, why do I choose to split it this way, that he
can be do the act of
making the ערך erech but not be on the
charts? מפני שריבה כתוב במעריכין יותר מבנערכין. Mipnei sheribah kasuv bemaarichin yoseir
mibene'erachin. The opposite of what Rabbi Meir said. There are people that
can be the subjects without being on the charts. Who can do
an ערך erech without being on the charts? Remember who's the people
that aren't on the charts? Jews that aren't on the charts? Less
than a month, but they can make an ערך. erech. Right, טומטום
ואנדרוגינוס. tumtum ve'androgynos. שהרי טומטום ואנדרוגינוס מעריכין. Sheharei tumtum ve'androgynos maarichin. The
people of mixed gender, right, they can still do the obligate or
indeterminate gender, they can do the be the subjects, make מעריך, maarich,
אבל לא נערכים, aval lo ne'erachim, they're not on the charts. So
the charts are more formal and are more limited. The same way
they limit you have to be of a definite determinate gender, they
could also be more limiting in terms of Jews versus non-Jews, the
charts are, you know, are more limiting. But who can make a
value? Anybody can make a value. Okay.
טומטום ואנדרוגינוס Tumtum ve'androgynos just assume ספק.
safek.
Yeah, but as long as he's not a זכר ודאי, zachar vadai,
the גמרא Gemara understands that he's not on the chart. Okay. אמר
רבא. Amar Rava. He's not even on it מספק. missafek. אמר רבא.
Amar Rava. הלכתא Hilchesa דבי רבי מאיר מסתברא, debei Rabbi Meir mistabra,
טעמיה לא מסתברא. teimeh lo mistabra. The פסק psak of Rabbi Meir
that he is that he's on the charts but can't make a
vow makes sense, but I don't like his
reason. טעמיה דרבי יהודה מסתברא, Teimeh deRabbi Yehuda mistabra, Rabbi Yehuda's logic
is more
persuasive, והלכתא לא מסתברא, vehilchesa lo mistabra, but his פסק psak is
not. It's very interesting, let's take a look. הלכתא דרבי מאיר מסתברא,
Hilchata d'Rabbi Meir mistabra, it makes sense that they cannot make the
donations. Why? Why does it, if you don't like his reasoning, why
does it make sense that they can't make the donations? Here's why.
A totally different reason. דכתיב לא לכם ולנו לבנות בית אלהינו. dichsiv
lo lachem v'lanu livnos beis elokeinu. When if you know עזרא נחמיה,
Ezra Nechemia, the book, when they were coming to rebuild the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, some of the non-Jews wanted to help out. And
נחמיה Nechemia said, you know what, this is our responsibility, not yours.
Now the reason is is because you don't know when you let
somebody in, you give them a certain amount of control and there
was concern about what type of influence they might have in the
building of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So therefore he says you
see that there is some reservation of having non-Jews donate to the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So now, as תוספות Tosafot points out, this
is not absolute. The משנה Mishnah said they could be נדרין, nidrin,
that they they could do vows and they could they could give
money to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. But it means if the
תורה Torah is excluding non-Jews from something, it makes more sense to
assume that there's some reservation, some limit about giving to the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash giving to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash as we
see in this story. And therefore the הלכה halacha that they're excluded
from being מעריך ma'arich makes sense, but not for the reason of
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. For the reason that from this story we
see that there are some reservations. Yes, Charlie? Okay.
So let's just finish this off. But so but טעמיה לא מסתברא.
taamei lo mistabra. So that that reason that I just gave makes
sense. His reason doesn't make sense. דקמייתי לה מחרשותא וקטן. D'kamaisei lah
meichershusa v'katan. He compares it to חרשותא וקטן chershusa v'katan that are
on the charts but can't give. That's completely irrelevant. שאני חרשותא וקטן
לאו בני דעה נינהו. Shani chershusa v'katan lav b'nei deah nin'hu. They're
not considered to have, you know, דעת, daas, to have
knowledge, awareness to make legal decisions. So that's why they're not they
can't do it. But a non-Jew does have that ability to make
legal decisions. So his comparison to חרשותא וקטן chershusa v'katan is invalid.
But his הלכה halacha makes sense because we do want to have
we do see from this story in עזרא נחמיה Ezra Nechemia some
reservation of having them make donations. Okay. טעמיה דרבי יהודה מסתברא. Taamei
d'Rabbi Yehuda mistabra. Now רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's logic
is more persuasive. דקמייתי לה מטומטם ואנדרוגינוס. D'kamaisei lah mitumtum v'androgynous.
He compares them to טומטם ואנדרוגינוס tumtum v'androgynous דאף על גב דבני
דעה נינהו. d'af al gav d'vnei deah nin'hu. These are people that
can make legal decisions. But nevertheless, חזינא רחמנא, chazina rachmana, the תורה
Torah excludes them. So the charts are somewhat narrow and you know
and excluding. It excludes people of indeterminate genders and also exclude non-Jews.
That's a good persuasive comparison. However, הלכתא לא מסתברא. hilchata lo mistabra.
It doesn't make sense to פסקן pasken like him. Why? Because based
on this story, דכתיב Dichsiv לא לכם ולנו לבנות בית אלהינו. lo
lachem v'lanu livnos beis elokeinu. Because of this story. This story persuades
us not for the reasons that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda gave, but to say if we're going to exclude
them from something, we'd like to more think that there's some reservation
about having them donate to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash because of
the possible influence that they might exert. It's not absolute, as the
משנה Mishnah says they can be נדרין, nidrin, but that makes more
sense to פסקן pasken like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir because of that.
We will continue with this fascinating discussion tomorrow about non-Jews making donations
to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and sort of more general conversations
around that topic.
What is נדרין? nidrin?
נדרין Nidrin is a vow,
which is just not ערכין. erchin.